<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-12T22:14:53-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Quantified Golf</title><subtitle>Better Golfing Through Data</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Understand your dispersion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/understand-your-dispersion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understand your dispersion" /><published>2023-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/understand-your-dispersion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/understand-your-dispersion"><![CDATA[<p><em>Picking better targets is an easy way of lowering your score.  How you select a better target is achieved by understanding your shot patterns (or dispersion) and overlaying that pattern to pick the optimal target.</em></p>

<h1 id="understand-your-dispersion">Understand Your Dispersion</h1>
<p>Dispersion is just another way of describing  what your typical shot pattern likes like for a given shot. Typically, it would look like a oval with some shots going longer or shorter than you anticipated, and some going left or right of your intended target.</p>

<p>As an example, if I tried to hit 10 8-iron shots, I know most will go 5 or more yards left of where I’m aiming.  A few good ones will be centered perhaps 5yds left of where I aim, a few more will be scattered out to about 10yds to the left, one might be exactly where I aimed, and one or two may be mishits and end up 20yds short and to the far right or left of the green.</p>

<p>Let’s lightly touch on some mathematical terms.  People often talk about <strong>standard deviation</strong> which is a term for defining how wide an area your shot pattern is.  If you are a beginner golfer, you shots will go all over the place or in other words, you’ll have a higher standard deviation than a PGA tour pro.  Often people use the term <strong>one standard deviation</strong> which means 2/3 of all shots will fall within that shot pattern.  <strong>Two standard deviations</strong> means that 95% of your shots fall within that shot pattern. With some minor caveats, once you calculate your standard deviation as a number, you can multiply it by two to get two standard deviations.</p>

<h3 id="calculating-your-own-dispersion-the-hard-way">Calculating Your Own Dispersion the Hard Way</h3>
<p>My flightscope mevo plus will do this for me but you can do it yourself with pen and paper (and a smartphone).  During a range session, hit 10 shots with a given club.  It helps a lot if you have a personal launch monitor that gives you carry distance.  Using <strong>carry distance</strong>, the distance where the ball would land is a better metric than using <strong>total distance</strong>, where the ball would come to rest.</p>

<p>For each shot, use the same starting line which will help you understand how much lateral movement you have between where you are aiming and where the ball actionally goes.  You absolutely should do your full pre-shot routine – just raking over the next ball won’t give you very accurate data.  As a bonus, I typically calculate two clubs at the same time by alternating shots with each club (e.g 5 iron and wedge, 7 iron and 5 wood, etc).  For each shot, write the carry distance down as well as how far left or right the ball goes, or <strong>lateral dispersion</strong>  (consider using left negative numbers and right of target as positive numbers). If estimating lateral distance is hard, consider holding your hand oustretched in front of you count the number of fingers between your aim line and where the ball lands.</p>

<p>I prefer to throw out mishits like shanks or super-fat shots.  I don’t think it’s super useful to include a shank that goes off 40yds to the left in determining your dispersion you would use on the course.   I find recording mishits are great at tracking your improvement, but when it comes to help you make better target decisions, I think it just adds noise.  How you define a mishit is up to you, but if you throw out all shots that weren’t hit perfectly, it’s not going to help you much eiher.  I recommend finding a middle ground what your shots will likely be on the course.</p>

<p>Once you have those 10 shots recorded, just throw the set of distance numbers and the lateral distance into a calculator like <a href="https://www.standarddeviationcalculator.io/">this.</a>  You’ll need the <strong>mean</strong> (or average) as well as the standard deviation.  So now what?  Let’s say my 8-iron shots have a mean of 150yds and a standard deviation of 8.  That means that 2/3 of the time my 8-iron will go between 142 (150 -8) and 158 (150 + 8).   To get 2 standard deviations, just multiple standard deviation by 2.  So in this example, 95% of the time, my 8 iron will go between 134yds(150-(8x2)) and 166 (150+(8x2))</p>

<h2 id="handy-shortcut-to-calculating-dispersion">Handy shortcut to calculating dispersion</h2>

<p>As you can tell, it’s a lot of work. I often use a shortcut on the course and compare my real dispersion with the shortcut and then calibrate.  For full club swings, I take the distance from the hole, and I use 5% of the distance as the standard deviation and 10% as second standard deviation.  So for example, if I’m 100yds out, I assume 2/3 of the time (ie one standard deviation)  I will hit it betweend 95 to 105, and 95% of the time (ie two standard deviations)  it will be within 90 to 110 yards from the hole.  Similarly, I may miss left or right by 5 yds or less 2/3 of the time, and 10yds 95% of the time.</p>

<h2 id="target-vs-aim">Target vs Aim</h2>

<p>Most people don’t hit the ball straight.  It’s really important for targeting purposes to figure out the center of your dispersion laterally as well as distance.  Using the mean, as described above, you may find your number to be +5yds to the right of where you aim if you fade or push the ball.  In that scenario, it’s important to aim 5 yards to the right of where you want the ball to land.  That means that sometimes, you’ll nut it perfectly straight and end up 15ft to the right of your target, but for every time you do that, more often you’ll land closer to your intended target. When selecting a target, use the <strong>mean</strong> or center of your shot pattern and then offset those distances to pick a place to aim.</p>

<h2 id="now-what">Now what?</h2>

<p>Ok, now that I have figured it out, how do I use it in practice?  Let’s say your lateral mean is 5yds to the right of your aim and your standard deviation with a 100yd wedge is 5yds, and two standard deviation is 10yds.  What I do is first make sure real penalty area like a water hazard is outside of 10yds reducing my risk of penalty down to 5% of the time.  Depending on how well you play a bunker shot, you may want to make sure you put your target 10yds away from that too.  Most bunkers at my home course aren’t that penalizing, so I’ll end up being fine aiming my target no less than 5yds away. Several places on my home course make short siding a miserable option, so I’ll avoid those as well.</p>

<h2 id="some-caveats">Some caveats</h2>

<p>All this math can be helpful, but there a few things to mention.  First, the math isn’t perfect in that it assumes a normal distribution (or if you hit an infinite number of shots on a chart, it would form a bell curve) which I don’t believe is true.  Typically, for a right handed player, if you charted your dispersion, the oval would be shorter to the right with a weak toey fade and longer to the left with a closed face pull.  I threw out mishits which of course I hit out on the course.  Wind, lie, and the variability of your swing each day will throw things off.  That being said, it’s still a useful tool.</p>

<h2 id="why-is-this-better">Why is this better?</h2>

<p>I find by doing this exercise on the course, I have three big benefits for myself.  First, scoring lower in golf almost always is about avoiding mistakes rather than making hero shots.  By selecting smarter targets, you reduce the risk of putting up higher numbers.  Second, it takes all the emotions out of decision making which also gives you more confidence in the shot.  If you pick a target that 95% of the time keeps you safe, that is a real confidence builder.  Finally, when you do pick a target and things go awry, there is some emotional detachment.  By thinking statistcally, sometimes you are going to dice is going to roll the wrong number.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="theory" /><category term="dispersion" /><category term="target" /><category term="course management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Every time you hit a golf shot, there will be a range of outcomes for where the ball will land. By understanding your shot pattern better, you can select better targets and avoid bad outcomes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Practice Game – 2 Ball Circle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2-ball-circle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practice Game – 2 Ball Circle" /><published>2023-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2-ball-circle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2-ball-circle"><![CDATA[<p><em>The 2 Ball Circle Game is a great way to work on those pressure packed short putts</em></p>

<h1 id="the-rules-of-the-game">The Rules of the Game</h1>

<p>The game itself is simple.  You start 2 feet away from the hole, putting 2 to 3 balls 6 inches apart circling the hole.  You start with the first one and work yourself around an imaginary circle around the hole.</p>

<p>Every time you make two putts in a row, move back one foot (e.g. move from putting 2’ putts to 3’ putts).  If you miss 2 putts in a row, the game ends.  A variation of this game is to do 3 ball circle wherein if you make 3 in a row, you move back a foot and if you miss 3 in a row, the game ends.</p>

<h1 id="why-its-great">Why it’s great</h1>

<p>I love this game because it really challenges you each and every putt.  Each putt is instrumental in either advancing or losing the game, keeping you challenged. Because you are circling the hole, each putt is slightly different in regards to the break, but not so much that you have to spend a lot of time reading the break. The challenge ramps up pretty fast.</p>

<p>My personal record is getting to 11’ which is well outside my typical game which ends somewhere around 6-7’ but many times much less.</p>

<p>Give a try!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;practice&quot;, &quot;putting&quot;]" /><category term="putting" /><category term="practice" /><category term="drill" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of my favorite putting drills is what I call 2 Ball Circle. It's a fun game and is great practice for your short putts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Principles of Putting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/principles-of-putting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Principles of Putting" /><published>2023-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/principles-of-putting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/principles-of-putting"><![CDATA[<p><em>Working on your putting mechanics is important, but don’t lose sight on these 3 principles of putting</em></p>

<h1 id="principles-of-putting">Principles of Putting</h1>

<p>To be good at golf, you need to be able to get the ball in the hole.  The vast majority of the time, that means pulling out your putter and rolling it into the hole.  To be a good putter takes the pressure off other parts of your game.  Conversely, to be a poor putter puts unrealistic expectations on your iron play and your chipping.  But what does it mean to be a good putter?</p>

<p>Fundamentally, to have a good putting stroke, you need to be able to consistent repeatable putting stroke that hit the face pointing at the target and that you can put the right amount of force on the ball for it to go the correct distance.  Other than that, you hold the putter the way you want, align the putter the way you want, and use your wrists and upper body the way you want.  While some ways are better than others, there are many ways to get the job done.  This is not to sayyou shouldn’t work on mechanics or take putting lessons from a teaching pro, but there is no single best way to putt.</p>

<p>So what elements of a putt are important beyond repeatability and distance control?  At it’s core, a good putt is one that roll <strong>the right direction</strong>, at the <strong>right speed</strong>, and has <strong>the right read</strong> such that it rolls into the hole.</p>

<h2 id="1-the-right-direction">1. The Right Direction</h2>

<p>If you want to be a consistently good putter, you need to be able to aim the putt where you want it to go and have it roll in the proper direction.  It sounds simple, but most amateurs could improve on hitting the ball on its intended line. The most important aspect of hitting a ball online is the face angle at impact of your putter.</p>

<h3 id="face-angle-at-impact">Face Angle At Impact</h3>

<p>According to the research, 90% of the contributing factor is getting the club face squared up at impact, while only 10% is related to club path.  Read that again carefully because it’s important.  Club path, whether it’s going inside out or outside in really doesn’t matter at all except when it comes to getting your putter face square at impact.  Club path can influence face angle, but the face angle is the most important thing you can do to putt online.</p>

<p>If a putt is 1° offline on face impact, you will miss a 10’ putt no matter how well you read the putt. Most good putters on the PGA can consistently putt within a narrow range of 1/2° of their target line.  That should be the goal for your own stroke.</p>

<h3 id="tools-for-hitting-the-right-direction">Tools For Hitting The Right Direction</h3>

<p>There are a few tools available for measuring face angle.  I personally love the <a href="https://blastmotion.com/">Blast Mostion Swing Analyzer</a>, there are other competitors who have recently hit the market.  The Blast Motion, which can measure other parts of your golf game besides putting, is a great device.  You put the device on the end of your putter and download the smartphone app, and it will tell you your face angle at impact and how much you open and close your putter face in your back and down swings.  For indoor putting, I find the feedback very useful.</p>

<h3 id="directional-test">Directional Test</h3>

<p>A cheaper option anyone can afford is a simple dime that you use on the practice green.  Take 5 balls and distribute them around a hole between 8 and 10 feet away.  Then for each ball, estimate the break and pick your aim point, and then placea dime 18” away from the hole along that aim line.  Now putt those 5 balls and record how many of those putts hit the dime.  If you can’t hit at least 3 of the 5 (4 of the 5 is much better), than I’d recommend working on direction control.</p>

<h2 id="2-the-right-speed">2. The Right Speed</h2>

<p>The second most important principle is getting the right speed on the putt to got the appropriate distance.  Many people have tried to determine the right speed of a putt to maximize the chance for it to go in the hole.  It’s clear  that the physics of putting dictates that  the slower the ball is going when it reaches the hole, the more of the hole the ball can enter and still go into the hole.  Conversely, the faster the ball is rolling, the more “on center” the putt needs to enter the hole for it to go in.</p>

<p>Does that mean each putt should end up exactly the distance of the hole and fall in with the last bit of speed?  Not necessarily. First, that gives you very little margin of error on putting the proper distance so likely many of your putts will end up short.  Also, because of wear from footprints, over time the hole will have an uneven  donut style depression around the hole – as your ball slows down, those micro depressions will have a bigger impact and cause the ball to go offline.</p>

<p>All in, most research suggest the best speed to get the ball in the hole is to aim to roll it <strong>12 to 18 inches</strong> past the hole.  That will allow for some margin of error in case you get the speed slightly off, and is optimal to reduce footprint displacement and maximize the chance the ball if fall in.</p>

<h3 id="anyone-can-get-good-at-speed-control">Anyone can get good at speed control</h3>

<p>Assuming you have at least average mechanics, you can get better at speed control.  Like any other skill, it just takes practice and of all of practice, I think most amateurs spend the least amount of time practicing speed control.  Even when amateurs do go to the practice green, I see far too many practicing mechanics and shorter putts over lag putting.</p>

<p>A simple drill is the ladder drill.  Start 10’ away from the hole (or better yet, just a tee, car keys, or ball mark), and try to roll it beteen the hole and 12”-18” past.  Every time you putt it in that zone, step back one large step or 3’, and repeat.  When you get to approximately 50’ reverse direction.   This simple but effective drill will undoubtedly make you a better putter if you do this 1-2 a week for around 15-20min.  I do it before every round to help me calibrate the speed of the greens.</p>

<h3 id="distance-test">Distance Test</h3>

<p>To test your distance control, find a place on the practice green that doesn’t have too many undulations and put two tees 40’ apart. Start on one end 10’ away and putt one ball from 10’, 15’, 20’, 30’, and 40’ away and count the number that reah within the distance of the tee and past it 18”.  Switch directions, and do the same going the other direction.  If you can’t get 7 out of 10 putts, then you shhould work on distance control.</p>

<h2 id="3-the-right-line">3) The Right Line</h2>

<p>The final element, after putting the right direction and the right speed, is making the right read for the putt.  For the most part, this takes experience and time to improve upon.</p>

<p>There are various systems, like <a href="https://aimpointgolf.com/">AimPoint</a>, that can help you read the putt better.  One key element of systems like Aimpoint is determining the slope of the putt and from that deducing the proper start line.  One good way to determine slope is to use your feet as a judge – it’s a learnabale skill and why you see AimPoint practiciners straddling the line behind the ball to feel which leg has more pressure.key element of systems like Aimpoint is determining the slope of the putt and from that deducing the proper start line.  One good way to determine slope is to use your feet as a judge – it’s a learnabale skill and why you see AimPoint practitioners straddling the line behind the ball to feel which leg has more pressure.</p>

<p>Regardless of the method, it all comes down to understanding the slope of the putt and then finding which line you need to aim for it to curve into the hole. That line will be impacted by both how well you stroke the ball in the right direction, as well as the distance you hit the ball.  The faster the ball is going, the less the ball will break.  Uphill putts break more than downhill putts (read that again because it’s counterintuitive and most people think the opposite).</p>

<p>An easy way to determine break?  Watch other putts (and chips) that can give you a clue including your own first putt so you are more likely to make the comebacker.</p>

<h3 id="right-read-test">Right Read Test</h3>

<p>While this is more difficult to test, one way to do so is the first test I gave.  Putt 5 balls down 8’ away from the hole in a circle, and read them, mark the start line with a dime, and then see how many of the balls hit the dime and go into the hole   Do this twice for 10 balls total.  If you missed a putt but hit the dime, your read was off.  If you missed the dime but made the putt, things get more complicated (eg did you just get lucky?, did you subconciously compensate because you under-read the putt?)  but in general, I believe finding the right start line and hitting that start line is the key to improvement. The PGA tour average from 8’ is 50%.  If you get less than 3, it’s worth working on, and trying to average 4 would put you ahead of your friends.</p>

<h2 id="final-notes-and-plot-twist">Final Notes and Plot Twist</h2>

<p>In reality, while those 3 principles hold to become a better putter, golf is more complicated than the physics we use.  Things like AimPoint assume the slope is eeven between the ball and hole which is unlikely.  The way the grass grows can impact speed.  Most modern greens have a lot of unudulations that make both speed and aim more complicated.  The grass grows throughout the day as your round continues and the water on the green evaporates throughout the day when it’s sunny. No green is perfectly smooth, and the speed of greens are different on every course.</p>

<p>That being said, the more you play, the more experience you gain and the better you will become.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;theory&quot;, &quot;putting&quot;]" /><category term="putting" /><category term="theory" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is easy in golf to hyper-focus on mechanics and swing thoughts. While having a good putting stroke is important, it's important not to lose sight on the fundamental principles of putting.]]></summary></entry></feed>